window.__examLoadCallback({
  "title": "Theory_of_Computation - Context_Free_Grammar — Slot 2 (15 Questions)",
  "duration": 42,
  "sections": [
    {
      "name": "Context_Free_Grammar — Slot 2",
      "questions": [
        {
          "id": 1,
          "question": "<p>If G is grammar with productions <br>\n\\(S\\rightarrow SaS|aSb|bSa|SS|\\epsilon\\)<br>\nwhere S is the start variable, then which one of the following is not generated by G? <br><br><strong>(GATE CSE 2017 SET-1)</strong></p>",
          "type": "single",
          "options": [
            "<b>A.</b> <p>abab</p>",
            "<b>B.</b> <p>aaab</p>",
            "<b>C.</b> <p>abbaa</p>",
            "<b>D.</b> <p>babba</p>"
          ],
          "correct_answer": "<b>D.</b> <p>babba</p>",
          "marks": 2,
          "negative_marks": 0.67,
          "explanation": "<a href=\"https://gateoverflow.in/118316/gate2017-1-34#a_list\" targer=\"_blank\" target=\"_blank\" rel=\"noopener\">Click here for detail solution by gateoverflow</a>"
        },
        {
          "id": 2,
          "question": "<p>Consider the following grammar.<br><br>\nP\\(\\rightarrow\\)xQRS <br>\nQ\\(\\rightarrow\\)yz|z<br>R\\(\\rightarrow\\)w|\\(\\varepsilon\\) <br>S\\(\\rightarrow\\)y<br><br>What is FOLLOW (Q) ? <br><br><strong>(GATE CSE 2017 SET-1)</strong></p>",
          "type": "single",
          "options": [
            "<b>A.</b> <p>{R}</p>",
            "<b>B.</b> <p>{w}</p>",
            "<b>C.</b> <p>{w, y}</p>",
            "<b>D.</b> <p>{w, $}</p>"
          ],
          "correct_answer": "<b>C.</b> <p>{w, y}</p>",
          "marks": 1,
          "negative_marks": 0.33,
          "explanation": "<a href=\"https://gateoverflow.in/118297/gate2017-1-17#a_list\" targer=\"_blank\" target=\"_blank\" rel=\"noopener\">Click here for detail solution by gateoverflow</a>"
        },
        {
          "id": 3,
          "question": "<p>Consider the following context-free grammar over the alphabet  \\(\\sum\\) = {a,b,c} with S as the start\nsymbol. <br><br>\nS\\(\\rightarrow\\)abScT|abcT <br>\nT\\(\\rightarrow\\)bT|b<br><br>\nWhich one of the following represents the language generated by the above grammar ? <br><br><strong>(GATE CSE 2017 SET-1)</strong></p>",
          "type": "single",
          "options": [
            "<b>A.</b> <p>{\\((ab)^{n}(cb)^{n}|n\\geq 1\\)}</p>",
            "<b>B.</b> <p>{\\((ab)^{n}cb^{m_{1}}cb^{m_{2}}...cb^{m_{n}}|n,m_{1},m_{2},...,m_{n}\\geq 1\\)}</p>",
            "<b>C.</b> <p>\\((ab)^{n}(cb^{m})^{n}|n,m\\geq 1\\)</p>",
            "<b>D.</b> <p>\\((ab)^{n}(cb^{n})^{m}|n,m\\geq 1\\)</p>"
          ],
          "correct_answer": "<b>B.</b> <p>{\\((ab)^{n}cb^{m_{1}}cb^{m_{2}}...cb^{m_{n}}|n,m_{1},m_{2},...,m_{n}\\geq 1\\)}</p>",
          "marks": 1,
          "negative_marks": 0.33,
          "explanation": "<a href=\"https://gateoverflow.in/118290/gate2017-1-10#a_list\" targer=\"_blank\" target=\"_blank\" rel=\"noopener\">Click here for detail solution by gateoverflow</a>"
        },
        {
          "id": 4,
          "question": "<p>Consider the following statements about the context free grammar<br>\\(G=\\{S \\rightarrow S S, S \\rightarrow a b, S \\rightarrow b a, S \\rightarrow \\epsilon\\}\\)<br><br>I.   G is ambiguous<br>\nII.  G produces all strings with equal number of a's and b's<br>\nIII. G can be accepted by a deterministic PDA.<br><br>\nWhich combination below expresses all the true statements about G? <br><br><strong>(ISRO CSE 2016)</strong></p>",
          "type": "single",
          "options": [
            "<b>A.</b> <p>I only</p>",
            "<b>B.</b> <p>I and III only</p>",
            "<b>C.</b> <p>II and III only</p>",
            "<b>D.</b> <p>I, II and III</p>"
          ],
          "correct_answer": "<b>B.</b> <p>I and III only</p>",
          "marks": 1,
          "negative_marks": 0.33,
          "explanation": "<a href=\"https://gateoverflow.in/995/gate2006-32-isro2016-35\" target=\"_blank\" rel=\"noopener\">Click here for detail solution by gateoverflow</a>"
        },
        {
          "id": 5,
          "question": "<p>Which one of the following grammars is free from left recursion? <br><br><strong>(GATE CSE 2016 SET-2)</strong></p>",
          "type": "single",
          "options": [
            "<b>A.</b> <p>\\(S\\rightarrow AB \\) <br> \\(A\\rightarrow Aa|b\\)<br> \\(B\\rightarrow c\\)</p>",
            "<b>B.</b> <p>\\(S\\rightarrow Ab|Bb|c \\) <br> \\( A\\rightarrow Bb|\\varepsilon \\) <br> \\(B\\rightarrow e\\)</p>",
            "<b>C.</b> <p>\\(S\\rightarrow Aa|B \\) <br> \\(A\\rightarrow Bb|Sc|\\varepsilon \\) <br> \\(B\\rightarrow d\\)</p>",
            "<b>D.</b> <p>\\(S\\rightarrow Aa|Bb|c \\) <br> \\(A\\rightarrow Bd|\\varepsilon \\) <br> \\(B\\rightarrow Ae|\\varepsilon\\)</p>"
          ],
          "correct_answer": "<b>B.</b> <p>\\(S\\rightarrow Ab|Bb|c \\) <br> \\( A\\rightarrow Bb|\\varepsilon \\) <br> \\(B\\rightarrow e\\)</p>",
          "marks": 2,
          "negative_marks": 0.67,
          "explanation": "<a href=\"https://gateoverflow.in/39594/gate2016-2-45#a_list\" targer=\"_blank\" target=\"_blank\" rel=\"noopener\">Click here for detail solution by gateoverflow</a>"
        },
        {
          "id": 6,
          "question": "<p>Consider the following context-free grammars:<br><br>\nG1: S\\(\\rightarrow\\)aS|B,<br> B\\(\\rightarrow\\)b|bB <br>\nG2: S\\(\\rightarrow\\)aA|bB, <br> A\\(\\rightarrow\\)aA|B|\\(\\varepsilon\\), <br>  B\\(\\rightarrow\\)bB|\\(\\varepsilon\\) <br><br> Which one of the following pair of languages is generated by G1 and G2, respectively? <br><br><strong>(GATE CSE 2016 SET-1)</strong></p>",
          "type": "single",
          "options": [
            "<b>A.</b> <p>\\(\\{a^{m}b^{n}|m \\gt 0 \\; or \\;  n \\gt 0\\} \\) and \\(\\{a^{m}b^{n}|m\\gt 0  \\;  and  \\;  n\\gt 0\\}\\)</p>",
            "<b>B.</b> <p>\\(\\{a^{m}b^{n}|m\\gt 0  \\; or \\;  n\\gt 0\\}\\) and  \\(\\{a^{m}b^{n}|m\\gt 0  \\; and  \\; n \\geq  0\\}\\)</p>",
            "<b>C.</b> <p>\\(\\{a^{m}b^{n}|m\\geq 0  \\;  or   \\; n\\gt 0\\} \\) and \\(\\{a^{m}b^{n}|m\\gt 0  \\;  and  \\;  n\\gt  0\\}\\)</p>",
            "<b>D.</b> <p>\\(\\{a^{m}b^{n}|m\\geq 0  \\; and  \\;  n\\gt 0\\} \\) and \\(\\{a^{m}b^{n}|m\\gt 0  \\;  or  \\;  n\\gt 0\\}\\)</p>"
          ],
          "correct_answer": "<b>D.</b> <p>\\(\\{a^{m}b^{n}|m\\geq 0  \\; and  \\;  n\\gt 0\\} \\) and \\(\\{a^{m}b^{n}|m\\gt 0  \\;  or  \\;  n\\gt 0\\}\\)</p>",
          "marks": 2,
          "negative_marks": 0.67,
          "explanation": "<a href=\"https://gateoverflow.in/39705/gate2016-1-42#a_list\" targer=\"_blank\" target=\"_blank\" rel=\"noopener\">Click here for detail solution by gateoverflow</a>"
        },
        {
          "id": 7,
          "question": "<p>Which of the following languages is generated by the given grammar?<br> \\(S\\rightarrow aS|bS|\\varepsilon\\) <br><br><strong>(GATE CSE 2016 SET-1)</strong></p>",
          "type": "single",
          "options": [
            "<b>A.</b> <p>\\(\\{a^{n}b^{m}|n,m\\geq 0 \\}\\)</p>",
            "<b>B.</b> <p>{\\(\\{w\\in \\{a,b\\}^*| w \\) has equal number of a's and b's}</p>",
            "<b>C.</b> <p>\\(\\{a^{n}|n\\geq 0\\}\\cup \\{b^{n}|n\\geq 0\\}\\cup \\{a^{n}b^{n}\\geq 0\\}\\)</p>",
            "<b>D.</b> <p>{a,b}*</p>"
          ],
          "correct_answer": "<b>D.</b> <p>{a,b}*</p>",
          "marks": 1,
          "negative_marks": 0.33,
          "explanation": "<a href=\"https://gateoverflow.in/39640/gate2016-1-16#a_list\" targer=\"_blank\" target=\"_blank\" rel=\"noopener\">Click here for detail solution by gateoverflow</a>"
        },
        {
          "id": 8,
          "question": "<p>A CFG G is given with the following productions where S is the start symbol, A is a non-terminal and a and b are terminals.<br><br>\\(\\begin{array}{l} S \\rightarrow a S \\mid A \\\\ A \\rightarrow a A b|b A a| \\epsilon \\end{array}\\)<br><br>For the string \"aabbaab\" how many steps are required to derive the string and how many parse trees are there? <br><br><strong>(GATE IT 2008)</strong></p>",
          "type": "single",
          "options": [
            "<b>A.</b> <p>6 and 1</p>",
            "<b>B.</b> <p>6 and 2</p>",
            "<b>C.</b> <p>7 and 2</p>",
            "<b>D.</b> <p>4 and 2</p>"
          ],
          "correct_answer": "<b>A.</b> <p>6 and 1</p>",
          "marks": 2,
          "negative_marks": 0.67,
          "explanation": "<a href=\"https://gateoverflow.in/3393/gate2008-it-79\" target=\"_blank\" rel=\"noopener\">Click here for detail solution by gateoverflow</a>"
        },
        {
          "id": 9,
          "question": "<p>A CFG G is given with the following productions where S is the start symbol, A is a non-terminal and a and b are terminals.<br><br>\\(\\begin{array}{l} S \\rightarrow a S \\mid A \\\\ A \\rightarrow a A b|b A a| \\epsilon \\end{array}\\)<br><br>Which of the following strings is generated by the grammar above? <br><br><strong>(GATE IT 2008)</strong></p>",
          "type": "single",
          "options": [
            "<b>A.</b> <p>aabbaba</p>",
            "<b>B.</b> <p>aabaaba</p>",
            "<b>C.</b> <p>abababb</p>",
            "<b>D.</b> <p>aabbaab</p>"
          ],
          "correct_answer": "<b>D.</b> <p>aabbaab</p>",
          "marks": 2,
          "negative_marks": 0.67,
          "explanation": "<a href=\"https://gateoverflow.in/3392/gate2008-it-78\" target=\"_blank\" rel=\"noopener\">Click here for detail solution by gateoverflow</a>"
        },
        {
          "id": 10,
          "question": "<p>Consider a CFG with the following productions.<br><br>\n\\(S \\to AA \\mid B\\)<br>\n\\(A \\to 0A \\mid A0 \\mid 1\\)<br>\n\\(B \\to 0B00 \\mid 1\\)<br><br>\nS is the start symbol, A and B are non-terminals and 0 and 1 are the terminals. The language generated by this grammar is: <br><br><strong>(GATE IT 2008)</strong></p>",
          "type": "single",
          "options": [
            "<b>A.</b> <p>\\(\\left\\{0^n 10^{2n} \\mid n \\geq 1\\right\\}\\)</p>",
            "<b>B.</b> <p>\\(\\left\\{0^i 10^j 10^k \\mid i, j, k \\geq 0\\right\\} \\cup \\left\\{0^n 10^{2n}\\mid n \\geq 0\\right\\}\\)</p>",
            "<b>C.</b> <p>\\(\\left\\{0^i 10^j \\mid i, j \\geq 0\\right\\} \\cup \\left\\{0^n 10^{2n}\\mid n \\geq 0\\right\\}\\)</p>",
            "<b>D.</b> <p>The set of all strings over \\(\\{0, 1\\}\\) containing at least two 0's</p>"
          ],
          "correct_answer": "<b>B.</b> <p>\\(\\left\\{0^i 10^j 10^k \\mid i, j, k \\geq 0\\right\\} \\cup \\left\\{0^n 10^{2n}\\mid n \\geq 0\\right\\}\\)</p>",
          "marks": 2,
          "negative_marks": 0.67,
          "explanation": "<a href=\"https://gateoverflow.in/3344/gate2008-it-34\" target=\"_blank\" rel=\"noopener\">Click here for detail solution by gateoverflow</a>"
        },
        {
          "id": 11,
          "question": "<p>Which of the following statements are true? <br><br>\nI. Every left-recursive grammar can be converted to a right-recursive grammar\nand vice-versa <br><br>\nII. All \\(\\varepsilon\\)-productions can be removed from any context-free grammar by suitable transformations<br><br>\nIII. The language generated by a context-free grammar all of whose productions\nare of the form x \\(\\rightarrow\\) w or x \\(\\rightarrow\\) wY (where, w is a string of terminals and Y is a non-terminal), is always regular <br><br>\nIV. The derivation trees of strings generated by a context-free grammar in\nChomsky Normal Form are always binary trees <br><br><strong>(GATE CSE 2008)</strong></p>",
          "type": "single",
          "options": [
            "<b>A.</b> <p>I, II, III and IV</p>",
            "<b>B.</b> <p>II, III and IV only</p>",
            "<b>C.</b> <p>I, III and IV only</p>",
            "<b>D.</b> <p>I, II and IV only</p>"
          ],
          "correct_answer": "<b>C.</b> <p>I, III and IV only</p>",
          "marks": 2,
          "negative_marks": 0.67,
          "explanation": "<a href=\"https://gateoverflow.in/395/gate2008-50#a_list\" targer=\"_blank\" target=\"_blank\" rel=\"noopener\">Click here for detail solution by gateoverflow</a>"
        },
        {
          "id": 12,
          "question": "<p>In the context-free grammar below, S is the start symbol, a and b are terminals, and \\(\\epsilon\\) denotes the empty string.<br>\n\\(S \\to aSAb \\mid \\epsilon\\)<br>\n\\(A \\to bA \\mid \\epsilon\\)<br>\nThe grammar generates the language <br><br><strong>(GATE IT 2006)</strong></p>",
          "type": "single",
          "options": [
            "<b>A.</b> <p>\\(((a + b)^* b)\\)</p>",
            "<b>B.</b> <p>\\(\\{a^mb^n \\mid m \\leq n\\}\\)</p>",
            "<b>C.</b> <p>\\(\\{a^mb^n \\mid m = n)\\)</p>",
            "<b>D.</b> <p>\\(a^* b^*\\)</p>"
          ],
          "correct_answer": "<b>B.</b> <p>\\(\\{a^mb^n \\mid m \\leq n\\}\\)</p>",
          "marks": 1,
          "negative_marks": 0.33,
          "explanation": "<a href=\"https://gateoverflow.in/3573/gate2006-it-34\" target=\"_blank\" rel=\"noopener\">Click here for detail solution by gateoverflow</a>"
        },
        {
          "id": 13,
          "question": "<p>In the context-free grammar below, S is the start symbol, a and b are terminals, and\\(\\epsilon\\) denotes the empty string <br>\n\\(S \\rightarrow aSa \\mid bSb \\mid a \\mid b \\mid \\epsilon\\)<br>\nWhich of the following strings is NOT generated by the grammar? <br><br><strong>(GATE IT 2006)</strong></p>",
          "type": "single",
          "options": [
            "<b>A.</b> <p>aaaa</p>",
            "<b>B.</b> <p>baba</p>",
            "<b>C.</b> <p>abba</p>",
            "<b>D.</b> <p>babaaabab</p>"
          ],
          "correct_answer": "<b>B.</b> <p>baba</p>",
          "marks": 1,
          "negative_marks": 0.33,
          "explanation": "<a href=\"https://gateoverflow.in/3543/gate2006-it-4\" target=\"_blank\" rel=\"noopener\">Click here for detail solution by gateoverflow</a>"
        },
        {
          "id": 14,
          "question": "<p>Consider the following statements about the context-free grammer <br> \\(G=\\{S\\rightarrow SS, S\\rightarrow ab, S\\rightarrow ba, S\\rightarrow \\varepsilon  \\}\\) <br> 1. G is ambiguous <br>\n2. G produces all strings with equal number of a's  and b's <br> 3.\nG can be accepted by a deterministic PDA. <br>\nWhich combination below expresses all the true statements about G? <br><br><strong>(GATE CSE 2006)</strong></p>",
          "type": "single",
          "options": [
            "<b>A.</b> <p>I Only</p>",
            "<b>B.</b> <p>I and III only</p>",
            "<b>C.</b> <p>II and III only</p>",
            "<b>D.</b> <p>I,II and III</p>"
          ],
          "correct_answer": "<b>B.</b> <p>I and III only</p>",
          "marks": 1,
          "negative_marks": 0.33,
          "explanation": "<a href=\"https://gateoverflow.in/995/gate2006-32#a_list\" targer=\"_blank\" target=\"_blank\" rel=\"noopener\">Click here for detail solution by gateoverflow</a>"
        },
        {
          "id": 15,
          "question": "<p>Which one of the following statements is FALSE? <br><br><strong>(GATE IT 2004)</strong></p>",
          "type": "single",
          "options": [
            "<b>A.</b> <p>There exist context-free languages such that all the context-free grammars generating them are ambiguous</p>",
            "<b>B.</b> <p>An unambiguous context-free grammar always has a unique parse tree for each string of the language generated by it</p>",
            "<b>C.</b> <p>Both deterministic and non-deterministic pushdown automata always accept the same set of languages</p>",
            "<b>D.</b> <p>A finite set of string from some alphabet is always a regular language</p>"
          ],
          "correct_answer": "<b>C.</b> <p>Both deterministic and non-deterministic pushdown automata always accept the same set of languages</p>",
          "marks": 1,
          "negative_marks": 0.33,
          "explanation": "<a href=\"https://gateoverflow.in/3650/gate2004-it-9\" target=\"_blank\" rel=\"noopener\">Click here for detail solution by gateoverflow</a>"
        }
      ]
    }
  ]
});
